[MUSIC]
[課程介紹]
Hi, welcome to this course where we'll try
to improve your statistical inferences.
歡迎加入「升級你的統計推論功力」
My name is Daniel Lakens,
I'm an experimental psychologist working
我是Daniel Lakens，我是一位實驗心理學家
現在是埃因霍溫科技大學HTI學群專任教師
at the Human-Technology Interaction group
at Eindhoven University of Technology.
我是Daniel Lakens，我是一位實驗心理學家
現在是埃因霍溫科技大學HTI學群專任教師
Now, some years after I completed my Ph.D,
I realized that my understanding of
幾年前我拿到博士學位之後，我發覺
statistics was actually not good
enough to design a proper study.
我對統計學的認識太少
不足以設計良好的研究
I joined the Reproducibility Project
我曾參與2015年重製100項心理學實驗
which has the goal to reproduce
100 studies in psychology.
的跨國合作專案
(參考https://osf.io/ezcuj/)
And when I started to perform
the replication study that I would do,
當我開始進行重製研究時
I realized that I had to
calculate an effect size
我必須先計算效果量(effect size)
to perform an a priori power analysis.
以及進行事前考驗力分析
Now, this is a very basic first
step when you design a new study,
今天無論進行全新的研究或重製研究
whether it's a completely new study or
a replication study, it doesn't matter.
都是第一步必做的功課
I realized I didn't really
know how to do this.
但是以前我並不曉得如何做
And then I wondered, well,
if I don't know to do this very first,
後來我醒悟，如果不知道如何做這些基本功課
basic thing,
how can I ever collect informative data?
我要怎麼收集真正有意義的資料？
Since then, I've been looking into how to
improve the way that we design studies and
從那之後，我深入學習增進設計研究的能力
draw inferences from data.
以及運用資料進行推論的正確方法
I published some papers on this, and
我發表過幾篇研究設計與統計推論的論文
(請見各週課程概要Overview)
I've realized that improving the
statistical understanding of how you do
我了解提昇統計推論的能力可以幫助你
成為做事更有效，更講究品質的研究者
research really makes you a more
efficient and better researcher.
我了解提昇統計推論的能力可以幫助你
成為做事更有效，更講究品質的研究者
So I'll share some of the insights I had,
and I'll try to prevent some confusion
所以我要分享我的收穫，以及幫助你
減輕使用R語言等統計工具時遇到的困擾
that you might have about
statistical tools that we use.
所以我要分享我的收穫，以及幫助你
減輕使用R語言等統計工具時遇到的困擾
The goal of this is to try to
prevent you from fooling yourself.
這門課的目標是幫助你避免在研究過程中
愚弄自已
As Feynman reminds us, the first principle
in doing science is that you must not fool
如同物理學家費曼先生的提醒：
從事科學的首要原則是避免愚弄自己
yourself- and
you are the easiest person to fool.
因為自己就是最容易被自己愚弄的人
So I see a better understanding
of statistics as a very good way
提昇對統計學的認識就是
避免愚弄自己的可行之道
to try to prevent you
from fooling yourself.
提昇對統計學的認識就是
避免愚弄自己的可行之道
Now, as an experimental researcher, the
goal might not be to do statistical tests,
身為一位實驗科學家，首要目的並不是做統計檢定
itself.
What you always want to do is
to say something about a theory.
而是根據某種理論提出解釋
So the goal of data collection is to
first draw statistical inferences and
收集資料的目標是先進行統計推論
then to draw theoretical inferences.
再進行理論推論
That's what you really want to know.
這類課程一開始都會先這樣的告知
But, of course, you need to draw a good
and valid statistical inferences
當然，統計推論必須要可信而且有效
because otherwise the next
step doesn't really work.
否則理論推論無法成立
So let's try to improve this step.
就讓我們由此踏上升級之路吧
There's a reason why psychologists,
maybe scientists more generally,
今天的心理學家還有更多科學家
有許多好理由提昇自己的統計推論能力
are now really interested in
improving statistical inferences.
今天的心理學家還有更多科學家
有許多好理由提昇自己的統計推論能力
And one of the first reasons for
starting on this improvement cycle was
其中一個理由是從康乃爾大學資深教深
a study published by
Daryl Bem on precognition.
Daryl Bem的預知能力研究開始
Precognition is the idea that
we can predict the future.
預知能力(precognition)就是人類
具有預測未來的能力
Now, you might believed that
this is possible or not, but
不論你相信或者不相信
as a scientist we should always keep
an open mind and look at the evidence.
身為科學家必須對被提出來的證據
保持開放的心胸
In this case, there was a set of nine
published studies that all showed
這份研究報告了九項實驗的結果
support for the idea that people
could predict the future.
而且一致支持人類具有預知能力
There were very simple basic tasks that
were performed that are widely used in
這些實驗都是實驗心理學常用的簡單作業
experimental psychology, but
the tasks were always reversed.
不過這份研究裡作業步驟都做了調整
So instead of first seeing a picture and
then pressing a button to
像是不用看到圖片再辨識
categorize the picture, the task was
presented in the reversed order.
而是請參與者看到之前就要辨識
People first had to press a button, and
only then the picture would emerge.
參與者按下按鍵之後，圖片才會浮現
So, of course,
想當然爾
you don't really know what to press
unless you can predict the future.
你必須有預知能力才曉得該按什麼鍵
And in this set of studies,
在這九項實驗裡
people were able to perform above guessing
average in most of these studies.
參與者的平均表現都比隨便猜的情況好
So after this, maybe some people
thought precognition must be real.
實驗結果發表後，有些人開始覺得
人類真的有預知能力
But other people thought, well, if this is
going to be published in one of the top
但是有些人在想既然社會心理學的頂尖期刊
(這篇研究刊登於JPSP)
journals in our field then maybe we
are not drawing the correct statistical
都接受了，我們卻無法從資料獲得正確的推論
(這篇研究刊登於JPSP)
inferences from data because it
seemed unlikely that this was true.
那可能是這些實驗結果並不是真的
(這篇研究刊登於JPSP)
There has been more criticism
in the scientific literature on
科學文獻裡已經有越來越多批判
how we draw inferences from data.
研究者普遍錯誤地運用資料做推論
Now, there are some people who
even go as far as to say that most
像這篇論文直接點出大多數發表的研究論文
報告的發現是錯誤的(false)
published research findings are false.
有些學者跳出來說大多數發表的研究論文
報告的發現是錯誤的(false)
Is this true?
真是如此嗎？
(第三章作業將深入認識這篇論文)
What do you think?
你怎麼看？
(第三章作業將深入認識這篇論文)
Do you think that most of the scientific
literature is false or not?
你認不認為大部分科學論文的內容都是錯的？
(第三章作業將深入認識這篇論文)
I think the answer is
we don't really know.
我比較接受的答案是「我們不會知道」
We can try to estimate it, but
we don't really have an accurate number.
我們可以評估出錯的狀況，但是永遠得不到
精確的數字
It's more important, probably, to try to
improve the way that we do research to
最重要的是，升級研究的方式可以避免情況惡化
prevent this from continuing on, so that
in the future we know that the data that's
未來進行的研究也能保障分析資料的品質
而能得到正確的結論
generated and the conclusions that
are drawn are most likely to be correct.
未來進行的研究也能保障分析資料的品質
而能得到正確的結論
There are some problems in
the scientific literature at the moment.
現在的科學論文充斥一些明顯的瑕疵
We know that many of the sample
sizes we collect are too small, so
像是許多研究的樣本數太小
we have underpowered studies.
導致統計考驗力過低
We know that people are very
flexible in how they analyze data.
還有因為研究者在資料分析過程中保留彈性
So this leads to a lot of flukes,
random findings,
這些彈性造成許多奇異又隨機但是不真實
的結果，卻被拿來當成真實效果
that are actually not true, but
people interpret as a true effect.
這些彈性造成許多奇異又隨機但是不真實
的結果，卻被拿來當成真實效果
And we know that there is
strong publication bias.
為人所知的問題還有出版偏誤
(publication bias)
People share findings that show an effect,
but
有的論文報告了顯示明顯效果的發現
they don't share findings
that do not show an effect.
卻不報告沒有明顯效果的發現
And all these things
make it very difficult
這些人為因素都讓評估已發表的研究
可不可信更為困難
to conclude whether published
findings are reliable or not.
這些人為因素都讓評估已發表的研究
可不可信更為困難
And the goal in this course is to try to
give you some tools to try this question
這門課程的目標就是讓你學會改善這類問題的工具
better, given that there's publication
bias, flexibility in the data analysis and
特別是由於出版偏誤，資料分析的彈性措施
以及低考驗力的研究，所造成的問題
low-powered studies.
特別是由於出版偏誤，資料分析的彈性措施
以及低考驗力的研究，所造成的問題
So, first of all,
從基本做起
we'll try to make sure that you can
draw better statistical inferences.
接下來的課程先讓你學會比現在更好
的統計推論方法
To achieve this we'll talk about p-values
and how to interpret them, report and
首先我們要談p值的意義，如何在報告
裡運用p值推論(week 1)
calculate effect sizes and confidence
intervals, but also discuss alternative
以及效果量(week 4)與信賴區間(week 5)的計算
ways and frequentist statistics such
as Bayes Factors or likelihoods.
也會介紹次數分配統計學之外的貝式因子
與似然性等等(week 2,6)
The second goal is to enable you to
design more informative experiments.
其次是了解如何設計能帶來充分訊息的實驗
To achieve this, we'll talk about how you
can control error rates when you design
為此，你要學會如何控制研究設計的錯誤率
以及有效執行高考驗力的研究(week 1,3)
studies, how you can efficiently
run high-powered studies.
為此，你要學會如何控制研究設計的錯誤率
以及有效執行高考驗力的研究(week 1,3)
But we'll also focus a little
bit on theory construction.
此外，還要認識一些理論建構的哲學思想
(week 6)
Another goal is to evaluate
the evidence in the literature,
這門課程還談到如何評估科學論文裡的證據
given that there is publication bias.
特別是存在出版偏誤的情況
We'll talk about p-curve analysis,
and we'll discuss publication bias and
這部分會介紹P-curve(week 6)以及
辨識出版偏誤的一些方法(week 7)
some ways to identify this in more detail.
這部分會介紹P-curve(week 6)以及
辨識出版偏誤的一些方法(week 7)
Finally, an important goal is to
facilitate cumulative science.
這門課的終極目的是推動有效積累
知識的科學
Of course,
we try to improve our knowledge.
人的一生都在不斷增進知識
How can we do this the best way?
不過我們能不能做得更好
We'll talk about how you can
perform replication studies,
我們會談到如何進行重製研究(week 7)
the importance of pre-registration and the
benefits of using pre-registration, and
註冊研究的重要性與好處
(week 3)
the importance of adhering to open
science principles in your research.
遵循開放科學原則進行研究的重要性
(week 7)
Accompanying these
lectures are assignments,
每一週都有搭配影片講解的練習測驗
and these assignments are really
hands on and in depth knowledge.
這些練習測驗都要深入認識相關知識
才能掌握
The goal is to learn mainly
through simulations.
多數練習是實際進行數據模擬來學習
I'm not a big fan of teaching
through formulas, myself.
我個人並不喜歡在教學中用公式講解
(我也是！)
If you're interested in that,
you can easily look up the literature and
如果你對公式有興趣，可以從各週導讀(overview)
I'll provide references where
these formulas are discussed.
找我推薦閱讀的論文，看更深入的討論
But in these assignments, we'll mainly
rely on performing simulation studies, and
因為這些練習測驗大多數是實做數據模擬
just seeing what happens in
the long run when you would perform
從模擬中觀察連續地(in the long run)
做同一種研究成千上百次，會發生什麼事
hundreds of thousands of studies.
從模擬中觀察連續地(in the long run)
做同一種研究成千上百次，會發生什麼事
Personally, I've found
that really informative
我的個人經驗是如此學習
能更深刻認識統計學
when I tried to understand
statistics myself.
我的個人經驗是如此學習
能更深刻認識統計學
We'll use R, which is free software.
每項練習測驗都會使用免費的R語言
You don't need to have a very good
understanding of how R works.
但你不需要非常了解R也能在測驗裡使用
We'll typically use very simple examples
where you can just run the code,
測驗裡的例子都很簡單，
只要你能執行我提供的源碼就行
maybe change one or two numbers.
測驗題只需要你更改源碼中的一兩個數字
(R初學者請從week 1練習作業)
That's really all you need
to know about how R works.
你只要知道如何執行R的源碼就行
(下載 Running R Code.pdf 閱讀實做)
Now, personally, as I started to get
a better understanding of statistics,
經驗分享，當我對統計的了解比較多之後
I felt much less uncertain and
我對數據的不確定感比較少了
much more able to draw correct inferences
from the scientific literature,
也更能從科學論文裡正確解讀結果
and to design studies that would
yield informative results.
並且設計能產生有充分訊息的研究
I really think that if you want to be a
good researcher, it's important to invest
如果你想成為好的研究者，投資一些時間
學習如何從資料做更好的推論是值得的
some time in learning how to draw
better inferences from your data.
如果你想成為好的研究者，投資一些時間
學習如何從資料做更好的推論是值得的
And it can be remarkable fun,
getting this better understanding.
學而時習之，不亦說乎
If you want to reach out to me,
如果想和我聯絡
you can contact me at Twitter with any
questions or comments you might have.
可以追蹤我的twitter帳號(影片右上角)
告訴我你的問題或意見
For now, let's get started.
現在！開始上課吧。
[課程結束]